3-42 Athabasca Hall, Edmonton, Alberta, T6G 2E8, Canada

Research Areas

My primary research interest is to develop and evaluate various program analysis techniques that can be used in practice by exploring three aspects: scalability, precision, and usability. My interests span programming languages and software systems.

Education

Ph.D., Computer Science

2014

University of Waterloo, Canada

- Advisor: Ondřej Lhoták
- Thesis: The Separate Compilation Assumption
- · Committee: Jan Vitek, Frank Tip, Reid Holmes, and Werner Dietl

MMath, Computer Science

2010

University of Waterloo, Canada

- · Advisor: Raouf Boutaba
- Thesis: Algorizmi A Configurable Virtual Testbed to Generate Datasets for Offline Evaluation of Intrusion Detection Systems
- Reviewers: Ian MacKillop and Urs Hengartner

B.Sc., Computer Science

2007

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

- · Advisors: Sherif G. Aly and Sherif El-Kassas
- Thesis: A Jabber Framework for Building Communication Capable Java Mobile Applications
- Minor: Mathematics

Professional Experience

Assistant Professor, Department of Computing Science

Jul 2017-Present

University of Alberta, Canada

Research Assistant Professor, Department of Computing Science

Jul 2016-Jul 2017

University of Alberta, Canada

Postdoctoral Researcher, Secure Software Engineering

Oct 2014-Jul 2016

- TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY
- Host: Eric Bodden
- Designing novel static analyses to detect misuses of cryptographic APIs in software systems
- Exploring new static analysis techniques that incorporate user feedback in a just-in-time fashion
- Developing various extensions to the IFDS analysis framework

Graduate Research Assistant, Programming Languages Group

2010-2014

University of Waterloo, Canada

- Conducted research for constructing partial static call graphs for Java programs
- Developed various call graph construction algorithms for Scala
- Studied static analysis techniques for various JVM-hosted languages

Graduate Research Assistant, Network Security Research Group

2008-2009

University of Waterloo, Canada

- Worked on various models of Intrusion Detection Systems: e.g., peer-to-peer, kernel methods
- Developed Algorizmi, an open-source evaluation system for Intrusion Detection Systems

Researcher, Department of Computer Science

2007

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

• Studied new techniques to support location management in Java-based pervasive systems

ISSTA, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis

ECOOP, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming

ISSTA, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis

SOAP @ **PLDI**, ACM SIGPLAN International Workshop on the State Of the Art in Program Analysis

Onward!, ACM International Symposium on New Ideas, New Paradigms, and Reflections on Programming and Software

SEAD @ ASE, International Workshop on Software Security from Design to Deployment

CASCON, International Conference on Computer Science and Software Engineering

Awards and Honors

2019

2019

2019

2018

2018

2017

2017

ITWORX, EGYPT

• Redesigned the graphical user interface of the stock brokerage system for Execution Ltd., London, UK

Awards and Honors	
ACM SIGPLAN Distinguished Paper Award ACM SIGPLAN SYMPOSIUM ON PRINCIPLES OF PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES	2019
Student's Choice Award University of Alberta	2018
ACM SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper Award International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis	2017
Distinguished Artifact Award European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming	2014
David R. Cheriton Scholarship University of Waterloo, Canada	2012–2014 \$20,000
Special Graduate Scholarship University of Waterloo, Canada	2012 \$2,500
Queen Elizabeth II Graduate Scholarship in Science and Technology CANADA	2012 \$5,000
Special Graduate Scholarship University of Waterloo, Canada	2011 \$1,000
Graduate Entrance Scholarship University of Waterloo, Canada	2008 \$3,000
B.Sc. Summa Cum Laude Honors The American University in Cairo, Egypt	2007
Best CS Group Graduation Project Award The American University in Cairo, Egypt	2007
Shell Endowed Scholarship The American University in Cairo, Egypt	2003–2007 30% off tuition
Professional Service	
PROGRAM COMMITTEE ORGANIZATION SPLASH-I Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, Languages and Applications: Software for Hurst SPLASH-I Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, Languages and Applications: Software for Hurst Artifact Evaluation Co-Chair, International Symposium on Engineering Secure Software and Systems (ESSoS) Demonstration Track Co-Chair, ACM SIGSOFT Symposium on the Foundations of Software Engineering (FSE) Program Committee Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN International Workshop on the State Of the Art in Program Analysis (SOA)	manity (SPLASH) 2017 2017 2017
Program Committee Member	
ECOOP , European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming	2020

ARTIFACT EVALUATION COMMITTEE MEMBER ISSTA, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis 2016 PLDI, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation 2015 **ECOOP**, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming 2015 **ECOOP**, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming 2014 WORKSHOP ORGANIZATION PLMW Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, Languages and Applications: Software for Humanity (SPLASH) 2019 Co-Organizer, Program Analysis Hackathon (Panathon) @ ECOOP 2019 Co-Organizer, Program Analysis Hackathon (Panathon) @ ECOOP/ISSTA 2018 Co-Organizer, Workshop on Benchmarking (BenchWork) @ ECOOP/ISSTA 2018 Co-Organizer, Compiler-Driven Performance Workshop @ CASCON 2017 Co-Organizer, SOAP @ PLDI 2017 Co-Organizer, WALA Hackathon @ PLDI 2017 Co-Organizer, Workshop on Designing Code Analysis Frameworks (DECAF) @ ISSTA 2016 Co-Organizer, Workshop on WALA @ PLDI 2015 REVIEWER TSE, IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering 2013, 2019 TOPLAS, ACM Transactions on Programming Languages and Systems 2018, 2019 **SCP**, Science of Computer Programming 2015 OTHER Co-Founder, Canada Open-Source Projects (CANOSP) 2019-Present **Co-Organizer**, Reverse EXPO 2018-Present Steering Committee Member, Undergraduate Capstone Open Source Projects (UCOSP) 2018 **Faculty Mentor**, Undergraduate Capstone Open Source Projects (UCOSP) 2018 Associate Editor, IEEE Software Blog 2017-Present **Web Chair**, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming (ECOOP) 2018 Web Chair, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA) 2018 Subreviewer, International Conference on Compiler Construction (CC) 2017 Research Funding **Validating the Correct Usage of Cryptography Libraries** 2018-2020 • IBM Centre for Advanced Studies Research Fellowship · With: Sole PI Amount: CAD\$60,000 Scalable and Precise Program Analysis for Modern Software Systems 2017-2022 • Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) Discovery Grant · With: Sole PI Amount: CAD\$125,000 Improving the Inlining Algorithms in the IBM Just-in-Time (JIT) Compiler 2017-2020 • IBM Centre for Advanced Studies Research Fellowship · With: Sole PI Amount: CAD\$90,000 **Publications** REFEREED JOURNAL ARTICLES Johannes Späth, Karim Ali, and Eric Bodden. "Context-, Flow-, and Field-Sensitive Data-Flow Analysis Using Syn-POPL'19 chronized Pushdown Systems". PACMPL, 3(POPL), 48:1-48:29, 2019. Distinguished Paper Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, Stefan Krüger, Patrick Hill, Karim Ali, and Eric Bodden. "Debugging Static Analysis". IEEE TSE '18 Transactions on Software Engineering, (to appear), 2018.

OCTOBER 9, 2019 KARIM ALI · CURRICULUM VITAE 3 / 6

OOPSLA'17

Johannes Späth, **Karim Ali**, and Eric Bodden. "IDE^{al}: Efficient and Precise Alias-Aware Dataflow Analysis". *PACMPL*,

1(OOPSLA), 99:1-99:27, 2017.

Karim Ali, Marianna Rapoport, Ondřej Lhoták, Julian Dolby, and Frank Tip. "Type-Based Call Graph Construction Algorithms for Scala". *ACM Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology*, 25(1), 9:1–9:43, 2015.

TOSEM '15

Sherif Aly, Sarah Nadi, and **Karim Hamdan**. "A Java-Based Programming Language Support of Location Management in Pervasive Systems". *International Journal of Computer Science and Network Security*, 8(6), pp. 329–336, 2008.

IJCSNS '08

REFEREED CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

Abdul Ali Bangash, Hareem Sahar, Shaiful Alam Chowdhury, Alexander William Wong, Abram Hindle, and **Karim Ali**. "What do developers know about machine learning: a study of ML discussions on StackOverflow". *International Conference on Mining Software Repositories*, pp. 260–264, 2019.

MSR '19 Mining Challenge

Artem Chikin, José Nelson Amaral, **Karim Ali**, and Ettore Tiotto. "Toward an Analytical Performance Model to Select between GPU and CPU Execution". *IEEE International Workshop on High-Level Parallel Programming Models and Supportive Environments*, pp. 353–362, 2019.

HIPS '19

Stefan Krüger, Johannes Späth, **Karim Ali**, Eric Bodden, and Mira Mezini. "CrySL: An Extensible Approach to Validating the Correct Usage of Cryptographic APIs". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, 10:1–10:27, 2018.

ECOOP '18

Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, Stefan Krüger, Patrick Hill, **Karim Ali**, and Eric Bodden. "VISUFLOW: A Debugging Environment for Static Analyses". *International Conference on Software Engineering (Companion Volume)*, pp. 89–92, 2018.

ICSE '18

Tool Paper

Stefan Krüger, Sarah Nadi, Michael Reif, **Karim Ali**, Mira Mezini, Eric Bodden, Florian Göpfert, Felix Günther, Christian Weinert, Daniel Demmler, and Ram Kamath. "CogniCrypt: Supporting Developers in using Cryptography". *International Conference on Automated Software Engineering*, pp. 931–936, 2017.

ASE '17

Tool Paper

Mona Nashaat, **Karim Ali**, and James Miller. "Detecting Security Vulnerabilities in Object-Oriented PHP Programs". *IEEE International Working Conference on Source Code Analysis and Manipulation*, pp. 159–164, 2017.

SCAM '17

Taylor Lloyd, Artem Chikin, Erick Ochoa, **Karim Ali**, and J Nelson Amaral. "A Case for Better Integration of Host and Target Compilation When Using OpenCL for FPGAs". *International Workshop on FPGAs for Software Programmers*, pp. 1–9, 2017.

FSP '17

Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, **Karim Ali**, Ben Livshits, Eric Bodden, Justin Smith, and Emerson Murphy-Hill. "Just-in-Time Static Analysis". *International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis*, pp. 307–317, 2017.

ISSTA '17 Distinguished Paper

Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, **Karim Ali**, Ben Livshits, Eric Bodden, Justin Smith, and Emerson Murphy-Hill. "Cheetah: Just-in-Time Taint Analysis for Android Apps". *International Conference on Software Engineering - Companion Volume*, pp. 39–42, 2017.

ICSE '17 Tool Paper

Johannes Späth, Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, **Karim Ali**, and Eric Bodden. "Boomerang: Demand-Driven Flow-Sensitive, Field-Sensitive, and Context-Sensitive Pointer Analysis". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, 22:1–22:26, 2016.

ECOOP '16

Steven Arzt, Sarah Nadi, **Karim Ali**, Eric Bodden, Sebastian Erdweg, and Mira Mezini. "Towards Secure Integration of Cryptographic Software". *ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on New Ideas in Programming and Reflections on Software at SPLASH*, pp. 1–13, 2015.

Onward! '15

Karim Ali, Marianna Rapoport, Ondřej Lhoták, Julian Dolby, and Frank Tip. "Constructing Call Graphs of Scala Programs". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, pp. 54–79, 2014.

ECOOP '14
Distinguished Artifact

Karim Ali and Ondřej Lhoták. "Averroes: Whole-Program Analysis without the Whole Program". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, pp. 378–400, 2013.

ECOOP '13

Karim Ali and Ondřej Lhoták. "Application-Only Call Graph Construction". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, pp. 688–712, 2012.

ECOOP '12

OTHER REFEREED PUBLICATIONS

Karim Ali, Issam Aib, and Raouf Boutaba. "P2P-AIS: A P2P Artificial Immune Systems architecture for detecting DDoS flooding attacks". *Global Information Infrastructure Symposium*, 2009.

GIIS '09

Karim Ali and Raouf Boutaba. "Applying Kernel Methods to Anomaly-based Intrusion Detection Systems". *Global Information Infrastructure Symposium*, 2009.

GIIS '09

Selected Invited Talks

"Is Program Analysis The Silver Bullet Against Software Bugs?" Papers We Love Conference, 2019.

PWLConf'19

St. Louis, MO, USA

"U Can't Inline This". TURBO Workshop, 2018.

TURBO at SPLASH '18

Boston, MA, USA

"SWAN: A Program Analysis Framework for Swift". NJR Workshop, 2018.

NJR at SPLASH '18

"Designing Tomorrow's Static Analyses - Addressing Scalability, Precision, and Usability". University of Colorado

Boston, MA, USA

Boulder, 2016.

Boulder '16 Boulder, CO, USA

"Designing Tomorrow's Static Analyses - Addressing Scalability, Precision, and Usability". Rochester Institute of Technology, 2016.

RIT '16

"Designing Tomorrow's Static Analyses - Addressing Scalability, Precision, and Usability". Iowa State University, 2016.

Rochester, NY, USA

ISU '16

Ames, IA, USA

"Evaluating Call Graph Construction for JVM-hosted Language Implementations". IFIP Working Group 2.4 on Soft-

ware Implementation Technology, 2015.

IFIP '15 Boppard, Germany

"Averroes - Letting go of the library!" Samsung Research America, 2015.

SRA '15

Mountain View, CA, USA

"Whole-Program Analysis Without the Whole Program". McGill University, 2015.

Montreal, QC, Canada

McGill '15

Master's

Research Associate at Fraunhofer IEM

Students

CURRENT

2019-Present **Spencer Killen**

University of Alberta, Canada Master's

David Seekatz 2019-Present University of Alberta, Canada

Ahmed Elkhair 2019-Present University of Alberta, Canada Master's

Ifaz Kabir 2018-Present

University of Alberta, Canada Ph.D.

Abdul Ali Bangash 2018-Present

UNIVERSITY OF ALBERTA, CANADA, (MAIN SUPERVISOR; CO-SUPERVISED WITH ABRAM HINDLE) Ph D

Kristen Newbury 2018-Present

University of Alberta, Canada Master's

Stefan Krüger 2015-Present

University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden) Ph.D.

2015-Present

University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden) Ph.D.

ALUMNI

2019

UNIVERSITY OF ALBERTA, CANADA, (MAIN SUPERVISOR; CO-SUPERVISED WITH JOSÉ NELSON AMARAL)

• Master's Thesis: Guiding Inlining Decisions Using Post-Inlining Transformations

Johannes Späth

University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden)

• Ph.D. Thesis: Synchronized Pushdown Systems for Pointer and Data-Flow Analysis

KARIM ALI · CURRICULUM VITAE 5/6 **OCTOBER 9, 2019**

Manuel Benz 2016

Ph.D. at University of Paderborn

TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY

• Master's Thesis: Interprocedural Data Dependency Graphs

Michael Appel 2016

TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY

• Master's Thesis: Call Graph Summaries for the Android SDK

Teaching _____

INSTRUCTOR

CMPUT 497	Foundations of Program Analysis, University of Alberta, Canada	Winter 2019-Present
CMPUT 229	Computer Organization and Architecture I, University of Alberta, Canada	Winter 2017-Present
CMPUT 620	Static Program Analysis, University of Alberta, Canada	Fall 2016–Present
SAS	Static Analysis Seminar, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany	Winter 2015

Co-Instructor

APSA **Applied Static Analysis,** Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany Spring 2016

SUBSTITUTE LECTURER

DECA	Designing Code Analyses for Large Software Systems, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany	Fall 2014
CS 241	Foundations of Sequential Programs, University of Waterloo, Canada	Spring 2013

GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT

CS 448	Security Engineering, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	Fall 2007
CS 125	Introduction to Programming Principles, University of Waterloo, Canada	Winter 2008
CS 456/656	Computer Networks, University of Waterloo, Canada	2008–2010
CS 446/646	Software Design and Architectures, University of Waterloo, Canada	Spring 2011
CS 444/644	Compiler Construction, University of Waterloo, Canada	2011–2013
CS 241	Foundations of Sequential Programs, University of Waterloo, Canada	2011–2013

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

CS 448	Security Engineering, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	Fall 2007
CS 330	Computer Architecture, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	2005–2006
CS 106	Fundamentals of Computer Science, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	2004–2005

Volunteer Work _____

CyberPatriot Technical Mentor, Strathcona High School, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada	2016–2018
Graduate Student Ambassador, University of Waterloo, Canada	Fall 2013
Tour Guide, Computer Science Open House, University of Waterloo, Canada	Winter 2012
President, Egyptian Students Association, University of Waterloo, Canada	2010-2011
Ushers Committee Leader, Honors Assembly, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	Spring 2007
Academic Committee Head, ACM Chapter, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	Spring 2007